A Guide to the Frederick T. Gates Papers FA028
Rockefeller Archive Center
Frederick T. Gates papers
1877-1939
FA028
Rockefeller Archive Center
2.3 cubic ft. 6 document cases
Bowers, Lamont Montgomery, 1847-1941
Buttrick, Wallace, 1853-1926
Eliot, Charles W. (Charles William), 1899-1993
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946
Gates, Frederick Taylor, 1853-1929
Jesserand, J.J.
Judson, Harry Pratt, 1849-1927
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1839-1937
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged alphabetically up until box 4. The alphabetical files are followed by three folders of abstracts, and an autobiography, scrapbook, and ledger. Gates' s own system has been retained.
Letters are frequently filed by correspondent.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
Biographical/Historical note
Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) was born in Broome County, New York. The son of a school teacher who read medicine and later became an ordained Baptist Minister, Gates spent the first fourteen years of his life in small villages and towns in New York. In 1867 his father joined the American Baptist Home Mission Society and the family moved to Kansas where Gates attended Highland University, a preparatory school. At fifteen he taught school and for the next five years had such various jobs as selling harrows to farmers, clerking in a village dry goods store and later in a bank. In 1873, he was admitted to advanced standing in the classical course at the University of Rochester, a small Baptist school. Instead of remaining in Rochester, he returned to Kansas for two years of independent study before he rejoined his class in 1875. On graduation from Rochester, he enrolled in the Rochester Baptist Theological Seminary and graduated in 1880.
His first and only pastorate was the Fifth Avenue Baptist Church in Minneapolis, Minnesota. In 1884 the church changed its name to the Central Baptist Church and moved to new buildings. Gates remained until 1888, when he became the fund raiser in a campaign to support the Baptist school, Owatonna Academy in Minnesota. After a successful campaign he was influential in the formation of the American Baptist Education Society and became its first Secretary. He moved to Racine, Wisconsin, and then to Morgan Park, Illinois, to carry on further fund raising activities, this time for a college which would grow into the University of Chicago.
It was in this capacity that he became acquainted with John D. Rockefeller, who invited him in 1891 to assist with his charities and investigate his appeals. This grew in time into a dual function of investigating and then managing some of Mr. Rockefeller, Sr.'s business interests.
Trustee of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, Trustee of the General Education Board, 1902-1928, and Chairman of the Board 1907-1917, Chairman of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease, 1909-1914, Trustee of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1913-1923, and member of the International Health Commission, the China Medical Board and the Peking Medical College, Gates resigned from business activities in 1912 and devoted himself to these philanthropies until 1928.
Scope and Contents note
Records consist of correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, memoranda, manuscript drafts, and a ledger.
Important subjects in the collection include religion, economy, medicine, philanthropy, labor, World War I, the China Medical Board, the General Education Board, The Rockefeller Institute, The University of Chicago, Consolidation Coal Co., the Merritt Case, education, homeopathy, agriculture, meningitis, diabetes, and theology.
Among the correspondents are: L. M. Bowers; Simon Flexner; J. J. Jesserand; Harry Pratt Judson; Frederick T. Gates; John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; Charles W. Eliot; and Wallace Buttrick.
Related Archival Materials note
Further records will be found in the Rockefeller Family Archives.
File Plan note
IV 2A 03
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Frederick T. Gates were deposited with the Rockefeller Foundation Archives in 1955 and 1961 by Russell C. Gates and Dorothy Gates Elsmith.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Original accession number assigned by the Rockefeller Foundation: 4
China Medical Board. U.S..; Consolidation Coal Company.; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.).; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.; University of Chicago.; Agriculture; Alternative medicine; Diabetes; Economics; Education; Labor; Meningitis; Philanthropy; Religion; Social service; Theology; World War I
- Lyman Abbott, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- E. Benjamin Andrews, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Philanthropy.
- "Atlantic Monthly", 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Baptist Church of Montclair, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- James Barton, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Gift to American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
- John A. Broadus, 1877-1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Wallace Buttrick, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Florence A. Cahoon, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Capital and Labor" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Unions.
- China Medical Board, 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Policy, mission hospitals, resignation.
- W. N. Clark, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Competition vs. Cooperation", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters of Congratulation and Complement, 1897-1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Congregational Church of Montclair, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Consolidation Coal Company, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Negotiations; B & O, Western Maryland railroads; Fairmont and Somerset fields; Northern Coal and Coke Company, Elkhorn Mining Corporation.
- "Corporations", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Harvey Cushing, 1907-1921 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Osler biography.
- George H. Doran and Company, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  "Red Triangle Girl in France."
- Charles W. Elliot, 1910-1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Philanthropy, medicine in China, agriculture, Germany, railroad strikes, American government, medicine and physicians, southern education, family life, industrial education, Howard University, World War I.
- Charles W. Elliot, 1910-1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Simon Flexner, 1908-1926 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Antimeningitis serum, homeopathy, Rockefeller Institute, epidemics, World War I, diabetes, insulin, influenza, pneumonia, religion, resignation.
- "The Financial Situation", 1903 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Prediction of 1906 panic.
- "A Forgotten Episode", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Socialism and the pilgrims.
- "Fundamental Principles of Philanthropy", 1908 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Gates Portrait, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- General Education Board, 1903-1926 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Policy, Rockefeller Foundation charter, Negro education, medical policy, gifts to state universities.
- Golf, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- T. W. Goodspeed, 1907-1921 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  University of Chicago history, Rockefeller Institute background.
- Health, 1906-1912 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Personals.
- High School Fraternities, 1903-1905 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Homeopathy, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Dr. Biggar, meningitis, allopathy, Samuel Hahnesmann.
- Hookworm, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  The Rockefeller Sanitary Commission.
- David F. Houston, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Insulin Gift, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Italy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36A)
- J. J. Jesserand, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Gift for trench soldiers.
- Harry Pratt Judson, 1908-1923 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Honorary degree, resignation from University of Chicago board, development of University of Chicago, World War I, submarines, academies, Oriental investigation.
- Landis Decision, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- "The Latin Race", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
- S. A. Lattimore, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Phi Beta Kappa.
- H. C. Mabie, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Shailer Matthews, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Medicine, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Medical education, medical schools, University of Minnesota, General Education Board and the Rockefeller Foundation appropriations.
- Dwight R. Meigs, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Classical education.
- S. J. Meltzer, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Merritt Pamphlet, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Letter on Missions, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Gift to the American Board of Commissioners.
- Missouri Pacific Railroad, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  B. F. Bush.
- William C. Morey, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  Outline history, philanthropy.
- A. S. Ochs, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Robert C. Ogden, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  Religion.
- Walter H. Page, 1906-1922 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Sir Horace Plunkett, 1907-1909 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  Rural economy, agriculture, publications.
- Polish Relief, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Albert C. Ritchie, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- John D. Rockefeller, Sr., 1892-1927 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  Philanthropy, Finance Committee, "World's Work" financial articles, gardening, Committee on Benevolence, education in China, church endowment, bank stocks, Oriental Institute, University of Chicago, world philanthropy.
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1907-1926 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  Stock market values and exchange, sectarianism, Institute of Economic Research, reorganization of the Rockefeller organizations, Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), hookworm, the Merritt pamphlet, Spelman College, compensation, University of Chicago chapel, theological seminaries, Christian College in Cairo, Colorado Fuel and Iron, L. M. Bowers.
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1907-1926 (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Laura Spelman Rockefeller, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 60)
- The Rockefeller Foundation, 1920-1939 (Box 3, Folder 61)
- Rockefeller Institute, 1911-1931 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  10th Anniversary, expansion, endowment, Business Board, Harold Swift, history, testimonial.
- Walter Rauschenbusch, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  Theology, social crisis.
- St. John the Divine, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 64)
- Shanghai, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65)
  Medical school.
- Albert Shaw, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  College athletics.
- "The Spirit of True Religion", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Stanley Committee, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  Merritt's Duluth, Missabe and Northern railroads; loans, consolidation.
- Testimonials, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
- William R. Thayer, 1914-1916 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  "Life of Cavour".
- "True Wealth", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
- University of Chicago, 1892-1908 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  Buildings, Rush Medical College, Dr. Harper, debt and endowment, gifts and withdrawal.
- University of Chicago, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  Testimonial.
- William Welch, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  Improvement of Johns Hopkins hospital and medical school.
- W. C. Wilkinson, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  Iron stock, Grant-Chase syndicate.
- Andrew D. White (Box 4, Folder 76)
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), 1910 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  Work abroad.
- Gates Papers, 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  Abstracts including the American Baptist Education Society 1892, states method, Negro education, Congressional Record of January 1917 on the influence of private interests on public education.
- Gates on Policy, 1905-1926 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  Abstracts, philanthropy as a science, reorganization of Rockefeller boards, world philanthropy, world medicine.
- American Baptist Education Society, 1888-1891 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  Abstracts from letterpress books, University of Chicago, Wake Forest, Baptist colleges, Cook Academy.
- Autobiography, n.d. (Box 4A, Folder 81)
- Clipping Scrapbook, 1907-1917 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  Gift to the American Board, the General Education Board, Women's Colleges, Frederick T. Gates, Rockefeller philanthropy, the University of Chicago, rural education, the Merritt case, the Rockefeller Foundation.
  General note
  Scrapbook not in box, as of September 2004.
- Personal Ledger, 1894-1916 (Box 5, Folder 83)